<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Discrete notes</title>
    <description>Blog</description>
    <link>http://discrete-notes.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://discrete-notes.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Popular matchings</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Popular matchings&lt;/em&gt; are a nice variant of the classic
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stable_marriage_problem&quot;&gt;stable matchings&lt;/a&gt;. 
In this post introduce these matchings, and give some bits of information about 
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;stable-matchings&quot;&gt;Stable matchings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember what a stable matching is. There is bipartite graph, where 
every node holds an ordering of its neighbours, known as the &lt;em&gt;preference list&lt;/em&gt;. 
A matching $M$ in this graph is stable, if no edge $(u,v)$ that is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in $M$ 
is such that both $u$ and $v$, would prefer to be matched together instead of 
the way they are matched (or unmatched) in $M$. Note that such matchings are 
maximal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stable matching always exists and can be computed in linear-time using the 
famous Gale-Shapley algorithm. Something frustrating with stable matchings is 
that they may be small with respect to the maximum matching (if one forgets 
about the preference lists). For example, in the following picture, the stable 
matching matches the top node on the left, with the bottom node on the right, 
and prevent the two other nodes from being matched, although all could be 
matched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/popular.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example shows that the size of a stable matching can be half of the size of 
a maximum matching. 
If you are in a context where you would like to (at least partially) satisfy 
the nodes in terms of preference lists, but you would also like to satisfy as many 
nodes as possible, then you need another form of optimality, and (max-size) 
popular matchings is a good one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;popular-matchings&quot;&gt;Popular matchings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a stable matching the matched nodes are happy, because they are at a kind 
of equilibrium, but the other nodes are unhappy because they are not matched at 
all. 
What happens if you make the nodes vote for their favourite matching? 
This makes sense if you do a tournament: for every couple of matchings you make 
an election, and the winner is the matching that is prefered by the majority of 
the nodes. In such an election the vertices perfer to be 
matched, and if matched consider their preference list. Also if there is an 
ex-eaquo then both matchings win.
A matching is popular if it wins every election.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;relation-with-stable-matchings-and-size-considerations&quot;&gt;Relation with stable matchings and size considerations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is known that every stable matching is popular. 
Thus popularity is a relaxation of stability. 
Unlike stable matchings, popular matchings can have different sizes, and in 
particular they can be
larger the stable matchings (that why we look at them in the first place).
Actually, stable matchings are the worst popular matchings with respect to size: 
stable matchings are the popular matchings of minimum size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then look for &lt;em&gt;max-size popular matching&lt;/em&gt;.
The good news it that a max-size popular matching can be computed in polynomial 
time, and that they have size at least 2/3 of the maximum size matching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got aware of this topic at a seminar of 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tcs.tifr.res.in/~kavitha/&quot;&gt;Telikepalli Kavitha&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irif.fr&quot;&gt;IRIF&lt;/a&gt; 
in September. After a nice introduction, she told us about her recent papers on 
the topic (there is a lot to say, with many relevant variants and nice 
algorithmic techniques).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of popular matchings was introduced by Gärdenfors in the seventies, 
who also proved that stable matchings are popular.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 
The polynomial algorithm for computing a max-size popular matching is much more 
recent, it was designed by Telikepalli and Chien-Chung Huang in 2011.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 
And popular matchings are still a hot topic.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;P. Gärdenfors, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/bs.3830200304&quot;&gt;Match making: Assignments based on bilateral preferences&lt;/a&gt;. (I couldn’t find it on Google Scholar, but it is accessible on Wiley.)&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;T. Kavitha, C. Huang, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ic.2012.10.012&quot;&gt;Popular matchings in the stable marriage problem&lt;/a&gt;.S&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://dblp.uni-trier.de/search?q=popular+matching&quot;&gt;DBLP “popular matching” search&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://discrete-notes.github.io//popular-matchings</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://discrete-notes.github.io//popular-matchings</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Start</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello. The start of the new blog.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://discrete-notes.github.io//start</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://discrete-notes.github.io//start</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
